<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A little catechisme, that is to saye, a short instruction touching Christian religion set forth by Theodorus Beza ...</title>
            <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09973</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 2023.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4128</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23231181</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23231181</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26414</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09973)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26414)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1807:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A little catechisme, that is to saye, a short instruction touching Christian religion set forth by Theodorus Beza ...</title>
                  <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Hugh Singleton, dwelling in Creede Lane, at the signe of the Gylden Tunn, neere vnto Ludgate, and are there to be solde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1579.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint taken from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"Cum priuilegio."--Colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Reformed Church --  Catechisms --  English.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26414:1"/>
            <head>A LITTLE Catechiſme, that is to ſaye, a ſhort inſtruction touching chriſtian religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſet forth by <hi>Theodorus Beza.</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Churche of God in Geneua.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>The firſt ſection.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>WHerefore hath God placed vs in this worlde?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> To know and ſerue him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>VVill he be knowne and ſerued according to our vnderſtanding &amp; wil: or according to that, which it hath pleaſed himſelfe, to declare and ſette out vnto vs touching the ſame?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> According to that which hee hath declared vnto vs concerning the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>VVher hath he declared and ſet out the ſame vnto vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> In that booke which wee cal the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, comprehending togither with diuers hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, the Law and the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>VVho hath made this booke?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> God himſelfe, by the miniſtery of his holy Prophets and Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>5</label> 
                  <hi>VVhat is the Lawe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> The doctrin which teacheth vs what we ought to do, as wel towards God, as one of vs towards another.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>6</label> 
                  <hi>VVhat is the Goſpell?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> That heauenlye doctrine which tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs, what we muſt beleeue to our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thorow Ieſus Chriſt only.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26414:2"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>7</label> 
                  <hi>Doth this vvord contayne all that which we muſt beleue and doe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> Yea, without hauing any neede to ad or ioyne anye thing thereto, or to take anye thing therefrom.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>8</label> 
                  <hi>Say novv the articles of your beliefe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> I beleue in god, the father almighty. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>The ſecond ſection.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>Doth this doctrine teach vs that there is but one onely God, or that there are more gods then one?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> It teacheth that there is but one God only, and that we may not haue more.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>VVherefore ſay you ſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> Becauſe it muſt nedes be, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he which is God, ſhoulde bee aboue all other thinges, and therefore hee may not haue a fellowe or companion ioyned with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>Yet you in naming God, haue ſeemed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe three, that is to ſay, the fathet, the ſonne, &amp; the holy Ghoſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> In dede there are thre perſons in one only Godhead: but yet theſe three perſons are but one, and the ſelfe ſame onely God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>Meane you that God is deuided into three partes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> No, for God cannot bee deuided, but I ſay, that euery one of theſe thre perſons is one, and the ſelfe ſame onely God altogea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perfect.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>5</label> 
                  <hi>How can this be?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> It is a miſterye or ſecreat beyond al
<pb facs="tcp:26414:2"/>
our vnderſtanding, and yet notwithſtanding moſt certaine and ſure, for God hath ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared it, and ſet it forth vnto vs, by hys ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly word.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>6</label> 
                  <hi>Doe you then beleeue ín one onely God, the father, the ſonne, and the holy ghoſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> Yea: and by Gods goodnes, will dye in thys fayth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>The third ſection.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>How is the ſonne of God called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> IESUS CHRIST.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>VVhat meane theſe words Ieſus Chriſte?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Ieſus</hi> is as much to ſay, as Sauiour, and <hi>Christ</hi> is as much as annointed and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to be our ſoueraigne king, hauing power ouer all creatures, our ſoueraigne or high prophet, who hath fullye declared vnto vs the will of God his father, touching our ſaluation, and our ſoueraigne or high prieſt, which hath fullye appeaſed and pacified the wrath of God againſt vs for our ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>VVhat hath he don and ſuffered to ſaue vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> He was conceiued by the holy ghoſt, and borne of the Virgin Mary, ſuffered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Pontious Pilate. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>Can God ſuffer or dye?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> No,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>5</label> 
                  <hi>Is not Ieſus Chriſt true and very God eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, vvith his father and the holy ghoſte?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> Yea.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>6</label> 
                  <hi>Howe then is he ſayd to haue dyed?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26414:3"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> Becauſe that being verye God, hee was made man alſo, to the ende that in hys perſon our nature might beare or ſuffer the whole puniſhmente due to our ſinnes and tranſgreſſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>7</label> 
                  <hi>Do you meane that the ſonne of God was chaunged into man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> No, becauſe then he ſhuld be no more God: &amp; God can not eyther change himſelfe or be changed. But being of himſelfe verye God, hee hath taken our nature vnto hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that ſo he might be very God and very man.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>8</label> 
                  <hi>If he had not bin God, could he haue bine our ſauiour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> No, for it belongeth vnto God only to pardon and forgiue ſinnes, and to giue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>9</label> 
                  <hi>And if he had not bin man, could he haue bin our ſauiour?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> If he had not bin man, he coulde not haue dyed, and therfore we our ſelues ſhould haue bin ſubiect vnto death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>The fourth ſection</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>Shall all the world be ſaued?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> No, for the greater part of the world refuſe their ſaluation.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>VVho then are they which ſhall be ſaued?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> They that haue fayth and beleeue.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>And vvhat is fayth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> A certaine perſwaſion and aſſurance,
<pb facs="tcp:26414:3"/>
which euery true Chriſtian man oughte to haue, that God the father loueth him, for Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt his ſons ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>VVherfore do you ſay for Ieſus Chriſts ſake?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> Bicauſe that wee being altogither corrupted and wholy peruerſe in our ſelues, God could not loue vs, but in reſpect of him onelye, which is man altogether iuſte and perfect, that is to ſaye, Ieſus Chriſte hys ſonne.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>5</label> 
                  <hi>Commeth this fayth of our ſelues?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> No, but from the onely grace and goodneſſe of God, which doth freely giue it to his elect and choſen ones.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>6</label> 
                  <hi>And they which haue this faith at they ſaued?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> Yea of neceſſity, for God hath giuen his ſonne to the ende that euerye one which beleueth in him, ſhould haue life euerlaſting: and he is not a lyer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>The fifth ſection.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>But vvhereby may a man know whether he haue faith or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> By good workes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>VVhich be good workes, and which be euill?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> Thoſe onely are good which he hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath commanded, and thoſe euill which he hath forbidden.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>Rehearſe now the commandements of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Heare Iſrael. &amp;c.</hi> The ſumme wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is, thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>To know Gods commaundements is not
<pb facs="tcp:26414:4"/>
onely to know to ſay them, but men muſte alſo vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that vvhich they ſay: wherfore I demaund of you vvhat meaneth that vvhich is ſayde in the thirde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, to take the name of GOD?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> It is to name God which we muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer doe, but vppon iuſt and good cauſe, and with feare of his maieſty whom we name.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>5</label> 
                  <hi>Then it is by ſtronger and greater reaſon more forbidden to ſweare by God in vaine, that is to ſay, to take him for a vvitnes and iudge, without iuſte and good cauſe vvhy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> It is ſo in deede.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>6</label> 
                  <hi>VVhat meaneth it to ſanctifie the Sabaoth day or day of reſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> It is to dedicate and conſecrate it to the glory of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>7</label> 
                  <hi>Ought vve not alſo to dedicate vnto him al the reſt of the dayes of our life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> Yea but this day is particularly and chiefely ordeyned for this end and purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>8</label> 
                  <hi>Doe men forbid to trauaile or vvorke on the ſaboth day, as thogh to labor wer a thing euil of it ſelf?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> No, but they forbid ordinary and vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all labor, to doe a worke which is better and more profitable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>The ſixt ſection.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>You haue ſaid that they only are good works which God hath commanded. VVherfore tel me can we acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſh &amp; fulfil the commaundements of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> No, not ſo much as begin to doe anye thing, but by a certaine ſinguler and ſpeciall grace of God. Yea there neuer hath bine or
<pb facs="tcp:26414:4"/>
ſhall be a man, excepting Ieſus Chriſt only, which hath perfectly fulfilled the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>VVherefore ſay you ſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> Becauſe God will ſaue vs thorowe his onely mercy in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>Yet ſo it is that a good life is the way to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> It is true, that repentaunce &amp; amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ioyned with the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes: but yet followeth not therevpon that we be ſaued by our workes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>And vvhy ſhall vvee not bee ſaued by oure vvorks, ſeeing that they are good?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> Becauſe they be not good ynough for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>5</label> 
                  <hi>VVherefore then are they good?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> To ſet forth Gods honour: to winne or elſe to ſtrengthen our neighbours, and to make vs know and feele in our ſelues, that we are the children of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu </seg>6</label> 
                  <hi>Good vvorks then make vs not gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> No, for contrariwiſe, a man muſt firſt be the childe of God before hee can doe good workes: but this is a marke or badge wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a man may know the children of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>7</label> 
                  <hi>VVhat then maketh vs the children and ſonnes of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> The onely grace and mercye of God, by his holye ſpirite, becauſe hee hath elected and choſen vs from before all euerlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, according to hys good pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>The ſeuenth ſection.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:26414:5"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>The holy ghoſt then is he vvhich maketh vs the children of God: but vvhat inſtruments or means doth he ordinarily and commonly vſe to bring vs to that honour and keepe vs in the ſame?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> The preaching of the worde, prayer, and the vſe of the Sacraments.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>VVhat call you preaching of the word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> An expoſition of the writinges of the Prophets and Apoſtles, which is don in the Church by ſuch as he hath called to that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miniſtry: of whom it is ſayd: he that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth you, receiueth me.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>Hovv doe you pray?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Saying.</hi> O our father which art in heauen. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>To whom ſpeak you theſe words?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> To God the Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>5</label> 
                  <hi>Hovv is he your father, ſeing that he hath but one onely Sonne, that is to ſaye, IESVS CHRIST?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> Firſt bicauſe that Ieſus Chriſte his eternall ſonne, being made man is become our brother: ſecondly bicauſe he loueth me in Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne, with a greater then a fatherly loue and affection.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>6</label> 
                  <hi>Albeit then that you direct not your ſpeach and words, eyther to the Sonne or to the holy ghoſt, yet you doe not exclude or ſhutte out eyther the one or the other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> No, for I can not cal him father but in the name of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte, nor pray vnto him but by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26414:5"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>7</label> 
                  <hi>And is it not lavvful for a man to frame or make his prayer to the perſon of the ſonne &amp; of the holy Ghoſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> Yea in deede. For ſeeing that the three perſons are one only, and the ſelfe ſame God, inuocation or prayer doth equally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto them. And whether I call vpon the father in the name of the ſon by the holye ghoſt, or that I make my praier vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue to lead and bring me to the father, or that I pray the holy ghoſt to teach me the father &amp; the ſonne, all commeth to one.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>The eyght ſection</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>And vvhat is a Sacrament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> It is a thing which God ſetteth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mens eyes in his Church, to ſignifie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs for our ſaluation, an other thing which men ſee not.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>And wherefore hath God ordeyned theſe ſignes to his promiſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> For to make vs ſo much the more aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of the certainty of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>Hovve manye ſuche ſignes are there in the chriſtian Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> Two, that is to ſaye, Baptiſme, and the holy Supper.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>VVhat ſee you in Baptiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> Water.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>5</label> 
                  <hi>VVhat doth this water ſignifie vnto you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> The bloud of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>6</label> 
                  <hi>To vvhat ende?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26414:6"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> To make cleane my ſinnes, as the water being occupied maketh cleane the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines of the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu </seg>7</label> 
                  <hi>Doth this water make cleane and purge ſins?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> No, but it ſignifieth vnto mee, that which waſheth my ſinnes, to wit, the bloude of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>8</label> 
                  <hi>Meane you that this matter or ſubſtance of the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt vvaſheth our ſoules?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> No, for our ſoules can not be clenſed with any matter as our bodyes. But this bloud maketh me cleane, becauſe that Ieſus Chriſt hath ſhed it for ſatiſfaction and ful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence for my ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu </seg>9</label> 
                  <hi>Is there anye difference betewene the water of Baptiſme, and common vvater?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> No, as concerning the matter and ſubſtance (for it is alwayes water) but there is very great difference, as concerning the vſe: for the common water ſerueth to waſhe and make cleane our bodely filthineſſes, and the water vſed in Baptiſme, is a ſacrament of the waſhing of our ſoules.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>The ninth ſection</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>VVhat ſee you in the ſupper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> The bread and the wine which is ther giuen and receiued, according to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and inſtitution of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>VVhat doth this bread and this vvine ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie vnto you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> The bread ſignifieth to me, the bodye
<pb facs="tcp:26414:6"/>
crucified for me, and the wine ſignifieth vnto me, the bloud ſhed out for me.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>To what end?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> To teſtifie vnto me, &amp; to aſſure me that euen as this bread &amp; this wine, are ordeyned for the maintenance and nouriſhment of this life, ſo our Lord Ieſus Chriſt hath giuen his body and his bloud for me, &amp; giueth himſelfe to me, to the ende that from him, as from a fountaine, there may flowe vnto me eternall life.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>Are this bread and vvine our ſpirituall nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> No, but they ſignifie vnto vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> from whence very eternall lyfe it ſelfe procedeth, that is to ſaye, from him which hath ſuffered his death and paſſion, to take away the cauſe of our death, that is to ſaye ſinnes, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue vs vnto eternall life, thorow a ſpirituall liuelineſſe, which reſteth and remaineth in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>5</label> 
                  <hi>Is there any difference betvvene the breade and vvine vſed in this ſacrament, and common breade and vvine?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> No, as touching the matter and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, (for it is alwayes bread and wine:) but there is very great difference, as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the vſe: for ordinary and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon meates are appoynted for the vſe of this preſent life, but this ſacrament is ordeined to ſignify and
<pb facs="tcp:26414:7"/>
ſeale vnto vs our ſpirituall and euerlaſting nouriſhment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>The tenth ſection.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>VVherefore hath the Lord ordeyned &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted tvvo ſignes in his holy Supper, ſeing that in Baptiſme there is but one onely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> To aſſure vs that hee doth not feede vs to the halues but wholly, being not only our meate but alſo our drinke.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>VVhere is Ieſus Chriſt nowe according to hys humaine nature?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> In heauen, from whence he ſhal come to iudge the liuing and the dead.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>By what meanes can you then which are on the earth receiue him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> As I receiue with my hande and my mouth the Sacrament, that is to ſaye, that bread and that wine, for the nouriſhment of this body, euen ſo by the vertue, and power of the holye ghoſte, I doe in wardly and in my ſoule receiue and imbrace thorowe fayth our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, very God and verye man, that by him I may liue eternally.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>Doe they which haue no faith receiue Ieſus Chriſt in the Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> No, for Ieſus Chriſt is not receiued but by faith, yet doe they in deede receiue the ſacraments, but to their condemnation.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>5</label> 
                  <hi>Hovv ſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> Becauſe that they make no differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwene common bread and common wine,
<pb facs="tcp:26414:7"/>
and that which is the ſacrament of the body and bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, whom they reiect and throw from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thorowe their vnbeleife.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>6</label> 
                  <hi>How muſt a man prepare himſelfe to come worthely to the ſupper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> If he haue true repentance of the life that is paſſed, confeſſing their ſinnes before God, and amending them towards God and his brethren, ſo much as in him lyeth, wyth a ful deliberation and purpoſe to doe better in time to come, and imbracing Ieſus Chriſt by a true fayth in his promiſes and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the alone and onely ſauiour.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu </seg>7</label> 
                  <hi>But hath Ieſus Chriſt left it vnto our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye and choyſe, whether vve will go to the ſupper, or not goe to it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A. </seg>
                  </label> In forbidding men to reſort thither vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth al them which haue iudgement and diſcretion, to prepare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues that they may repaire worthily to it.</p>
               <closer>God giue vs all grace to go to it, to his honor and glory, and to our ſaluation. So be it.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A prayer to be ſayd of children be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſtudy their leſſon</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein ſhall a childe addreſſe his way, in guiding himſelfe according to thy word O Lord. Open our eyes &amp; we ſhall conſider the maruailous things of thy law. Giue vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and we ſhal keepe thy law, yea we will keepe it with our heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26414:8"/>O Lord whych art the fountaine of al wiſedom and knovveldge, ſeing it hath pleaſed thee to giue vs the meane to be taughte in our young age to knovve howe to guide our ſelues holily and honeſtly, in al the reſt of our life here after to come, let it pleaſe thee alſo to lighten our vnderſtanding (vvhyche of it ſelfe is blind) that it may comprehend and receiue that doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and learning, vvhich ſhall be taught vs, confirme alſo and ſtrengthen our memorye to keepe it wel: diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our hearts to receiue the ſame vvillingly, &amp; with ſuch deſire as is mete, leaſt that thorovv our vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, the occaſion that thou doſt offer vnto vs, ſhuld periſh or be loſt. To this end powre vpon vs we pray thee thy holye ſpirite, vvhich is the ſpirite of all vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, truth, iudgemente, vviſedome and learning, which may make vs able to profit ſo wel that the pain vvhich ſhall be taken in teaching vs be not loſt. And to whatſoeuer ſtudy, that we apply our ſelues, graunte that we may refer it to the true and right ende, vvhich is to knovve thee, in our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, that vve may haue ful truſt of our ſaluation and eternal life in thy grace, and may ſerue thee vprightlye and purelye, according to thy good pleaſure, ſo that al that which we ſhall learn, may be an inſtrument to help vs therto And ſeeing that thou doeſt promyſe to giue vvyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the little ones, and ſuch as are humble, and on the otherſide to confound the proud in the vanity of their wits and vnderſtandinges: &amp; likewiſe to make thy ſelfe knowen vnto them that bee of an vpryght hart, &amp; on the otherſide to make blinde the wicked &amp; vngodly, vve beſeche thee to faſhion and ſubdue vs to true humility, that thereby vve may be made apte to learne &amp; obedient alſo, firſt vnto thee, ſecondly vnto our ſuperiors which thou haſt appoynted to gouerne
<pb facs="tcp:26414:8"/>
and teach vs. Moreouer, vve hartily praye thee to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and frame our harts, vnfeynedly to ſeeke thee, for ſaking all fleſhly and euil affections, and that vve maye nowe in ſuch ſorte prepare our ſelues, to ſerue thee hereafter in that eſtate and calling, vvhyche it ſhall pleaſe thee to ordeyne and appoynt for vs, vvhen vve ſhall come to age. Heare vs O father of all mercy tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row our Lord Ieſus Chriſte. So bee it.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSALME. XXV.</bibl>
               <q>The Lorde reuealeth his ſecretes, vnto them which feare him, and maketh them to knowe his couenaunte.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Jmprinted at London by Hugh Singleton, dwelling in Creede Lane, at the ſigne of the gylden Tunn, neere vnto Ludgate, and are there to be ſolde.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno.</hi> 1579.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>insignia of printer</figDesc>
               <p>HS</p>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
